A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries xFA118
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
xFA118
1 Cubic Feet Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable.
Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan
RG 12
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office
Scope and Contents
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential., The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
The Foundation's archives include:
Projects General Correspondence Administration, Program and Policy China Medical Board International Health Board/Division Field Offices Treasurer's Office Comptroller Personnel Fellowships Information Services Diaries Oral Histories Counsel Secretary Minutes and Officers Actions Dockets Declinations (100F) Non-textual Materials Communications Office
Conditions Governing Access
Officers' diaries are open for scholarly research provided that (1) the diarist is deceased and (2) the volume to be examined is at least twenty years old. All reasonable efforts will be made to determine the fate of the diarist(s), but if such efforts are fruitless then the material will remain closed to scholarly research until 100 years after the officer's year of birth.
Epidemics; Race and society; African Americans; Diseases; Life sciences; Philanthropy; Arts; Humanities; Medical sciences; Public health; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; Philanthropy -- United States; Rockefeller Foundation
- Aitken, Thomas H. G.
  - 1946-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
- Albaugh, Leland G.
  - 1948 (Box 1)
- Allen, Jane
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted - RF Officer Diaries.
  - 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - 1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
- Allen, LeRoy R.
  Biographical / Historical
  Born 1913.
  - 1957- 1961 November (Box 3)
  - 1961 December-1962 (Box 4)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - 1968 (Box 4)
- Anderson, Charles R.
  - 1952-1955 (Box 5)
- Anderson, Richmond K.
  - 1947-1950 (Box 5)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - 1955 (Box 6)
  - 1956 January-June (Box 6)
  - 1956 July-December (Box 7)
  - 1957 January-June (Box 7)
  - 1957 July-December (Box 7)
  - 1958 January-April (Box 8)
  - 1958 May-December (Box 8)
  - 1959 January-May (Box 8)
  - 1959 June-December (Box 9)
  - 1960 January-June (Box 9)
  - 1960 July-December (Box 9)
  - 1961 January-March (Box 10)
  - 1961 April-August (Box 10)
  - 1961 September-December (Box 10)
  - 1962 January-March (Box 11)
  - 1962 April-December (Box 11)
  - 1963 January-May (Box 11)
  - 1963 June-December (Box 11)
  - 1964 (Box 12)
- App, Alva A.
  - 1983-1987 (Box 12)
- Appleget, Thomas B.
  - 1929 (Box 12)
  - 1930 (Box 13)
  - 1931 (Box 13)
  - 1932 (Box 14)
  - 1933 (Box 14)
  - 1934 (Box 14)
  - 1935 (Box 14)
  - 1936 (Box 15)
  - 1937 (Box 15)
  - 1938 (Box 15)
  - 1939 (Box 15)
  - 1940 (Box 16)
  - 1941 (Box 16)
  - 1942 (Box 16)
  - 1943 (Box 16)
  - 1944 (Box 16)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 17)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 17)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 17)
- Arbab, Farzam
  - 1974-1977 (Box 18)
- Arnold, Virginia
  - 1956-1957 (Box 18A)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Diary is unaccounted for and currently unavailble for scholarly access
  - 1957 (Box 18A)
    Diary is unaccounted for and currently unavailable for scholarly access
  - 1958 (Box 18A)
  - 1959 (Box 18)
  - 1960 (Box 18)
  - 1961 (Box 19)
  - 1962 (Box 19)
  - 1963 (Box 20)
  - 1964 (Box 20)
  - 1965 (Box 21)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 21)
- Baird, Guy B.
  - 1958-1961 (Box 21)
  - 1962 (Box 22)
  - 1963-1966 (Box 22)
  - 1967-1969 (Box 22)
  - 1969 December- 1970 February (Box 23)
  - 1970 March-May (Box 23)
  - 1970 July (Box 23)
  - 1970 Septmeber-November (Box 23)
  - 1971 March-July (Box 23)
  - 1971 September-December (Box 23)
- Bakeman, George W.
  - 1926-1927 (Box 23)
- Balfour, Marshall C.
  - 1939, 1943-1944 (Box 23)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 23)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 24)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 24)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 24)
  - 1958-1960 (Box 24)
- Barnard, Chester I.
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files are available through the RAC website, and user copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  - Index, 1948-1952 (Reel M Bar 1, Frame 1, Box 25)
    Scope and Contents note
    Index to diary 1948-1952. Organized by the person, organization, or institution interviewed
    indexes (reference sources); Rockefeller Foundation; Barnard, Chester Irving
  - 1948 August 18-1952 May 29 (Reel M Bar 1, Frame 4, Box 25)
    Organized by interview, entries for this period record the meetings and telephone conversations that took place between Barnard and seekers of RF funding or fellowships. Noteworthy interlocutors (and their positions at the time) include James B. Conant, the president of Harvard University; Lewis W. Douglas, United States Ambassador to the United Kingdom; Joseph C. Grew, former U.S. Ambassador to Japan; and John J. McCloy, U.S. High Commissioner for Germany. Lengthy conversations with John J. McCloy include McCloy’s perceptions of postwar Germany and attitudes toward German reorientation. Barnard’s own opinion of postwar Germany is included in the section entitled “Notes on German Attitude,” and is located within notes on his trip to Europe. A personal conversation between John D Rockefeller Jr. and Barnard is embedded within the entries. The discussion centered upon JDR’s opposition to the phrase “distributing wealth for the public good” as was written in a draft of the RF history.
    Diaries; Barnard, Chester Irving; Rockefeller Foundation
- Barnes, Allan C.
  - 1970-1975 (Box 26)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 26)
- Barnish, Guy
  - 1969-1978 (Box 27)
- Bates, Marston
  - 1948-1949 (Box 27)
- Bauer, Johannes H.
  - 1935-1939 (Box 27)
  - 1940-1944 (Box 28)
  - 1945-1947 (Box 28)
  - 1948-1951 (Box 28)
  - 1952 (Box 29)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 29)
- Beach, Byron
  - 1921 (Box 29)
- Beard, Mary
  - 1925 December 4-1926 December 31 (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Nursing education programs—both domestic and international—are discussed and schools of nursing located within the U.S. are visited and surveyed. The subject matter of the diaries includes nursing and public health; women’s health; child health; maternal care; child care; and nursing education. A copy of “Listening On” a pamphlet published by the National Organization for Public Health Nursing (October 1926) is also included in this diary. (New York, Yale School of Nursing New Haven)
    Nursing care plans; Nursing; Diaries; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; Yale University. School of Nursing
  - 1927 (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 171)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. A theme during this year’s entries is the advancement of the nursing profession in the US and abroad. International nursing fellows are hosted at US and Canadian institutions and the state of public health in communities with and without nursing personnel is assessed. Other subject matter includes general public health; hospital organization; nursing organization within wards; nursing higher education; and nursing professionalization. (Yale School of Nursing New Haven, Toronto)
    Public health; Public health nursing; Diaries; Yale University. School of Nursing; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1928 (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 386)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard tours nursing establishments across the country including hospitals, nursing universities, and clinics and reports on the state of nursing at each institution. Specific subjects addressed include nursing theory; nursing and public health education; the professionalization of nursing; the cost of nursing to hospitals; the organization of the nursing service; and the activities of committees dedicated to nursing affairs.
    Public health nursing; Diaries; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; Yale University. School of Nursing
  - 1929 (Reel M Bea 1, Frame 537, Box 30)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Development—and proliferation—of public health nursing is the principal objective of Beard’s visits, interviews, and activities for this year. Concerning domestic development, Beard surveys the nursing profession in a number of U.S. cities, and concerning international development, Beard is involved in sponsoring international women to study in the US on RF fellowships. The integration of African-Americans into the nursing profession is also discussed throughout the entries.
    Diaries; Public health nursing; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1930 (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 696)
    While on an extensive tour of Europe and Asia, Beard meets with international nursing professionals and surveys the state of nursing education in a wide array of countries including—but not limited to—China, India, Singapore, Israel, Egypt, and the United Kingdom. Upon her return, Beard continues her work managing the education of RF fellows from foreign countries; promoting the development of public health nursing in the U.S and abroad; and standardizing the education of nursing professionals. A map entitled “China, Siam, Indo-China, and Chosen,” is embedded within the entries and is dated 1915.
  - 1931 (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 864)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows—both American and foreign—and discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries.
    Diaries; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1932 (Reel M Bea 1, Frame 972, Box 30)
    Temporarily based at the RF Paris Office, Beard meets with fellow public health nursing officer Elizabeth Crowell and tours various European cities where the RF has invested funds in nursing and/or public health programs. Entries record her impressions of programs and fellowship recipients as well as suggestions for the future. Cities included in the European tour include Warsaw, Krakow, Vienna, Graz, Cluj, Budapest, Debrecen, Skoplje, Belgrade, Zagreb, and Rome. Upon returning to the NY office, Beard continues her duties as a public health nursing consultant for various RF programs across the United States. Included in this years' entries are preliminary surveys and impressions of public health in various cities located in Pakistan, India, and Sri Lanka.
    Nursing care plans; Nursing; Public health nursing; Diaries; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1933 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Folder 1)
    Organized according to visit and interview, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Entries record her various impressions of maternity hospitals, child welfare centers and nursing/medical schools in Burma, India and Sri Lanka. Upon her return, discusses trip abroad, fellowships for public health nurses and nursing education. Also, Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both American and foreign- and discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries.
    Diaries; Public health nursing; Nursing care plans; Nursing; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1934 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 102)
    Organized according to interview or view, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Nursing education programs –both domestic and international- are discussed and schools of nursing located within the U.S. are visited and surveyed. Main topics in this diary include reorganizing public health nursing programs in Washington County, New York, Vanderbilt University, University of Toronto and New York Hospital. Beard is also involved with the selection process and mentorship of RF fellowship nursing applicants. A copy of “Act of Parliament of the Council of the School of Nursing, University of Toronto” is included as well as an outline review of New York Hospital’s budgetary crisis regarding its nursing services and how to build up present nursing organization.
    Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; Nursing; Diaries; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1935 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 244)
    The diary is organized according to interview and visit. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows—both American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. Throughout the year, development of public health nursing programs continues at Columbia University, Vanderbilt University and Washington County, New York. Beard opens discussion for development of school of nursing between Russell Sage College in Troy, New York, and Albany Medical School and Albany General Hospital. Brief travels to Europe, specifically England to discuss organizing and supplying grant money to set up Florence Nightingale School of Nursing in England. A copy of “East Harlem Nursing and Health Service” is included.
    Nursing; Public health nursing; Nursing care plans; Diaries; England; France; United States; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation
  - 1936 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 351)
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. Beard continues to develop, reorganize and establish nursing education programs at various institutions around the country such as Vanderbilt University, Russell Sage, John Hopkins and Skidmore College. Beard also details the limitations and setbacks of developing public health nursing education programs at the advanced level. The diary describes the hardships of rural Southern nurses and how the Tennessee Valley Authority Health Study makes an impact on the region. Beard sets up talks to develop a School of Nursing at University of California at Los Angeles. She travels to Panama to develop nursing education programs in the region. A copy of "Minutes of the Meeting of the Advisory Committee on Nursing, of the Department of Health", a graph of "Various Types of Schools of nursing in the United States (1936)", "Minutes of the Council of Course Directors" and "Visiting Nurse Association" documents, a pamphlet entitled "Baby Record" put out by the Child Welfare Division, Department of Health and Sanitation, Seattle, Washington as well as a pamphlet distributed by the Public Education Association entitled "what It is and What It Does" are included.
    Diaries; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; United States; Panama; Canada; Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation
  - Trip Index, 1937 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 502)
    Trip Index to Diary:1937; nineteen pages.
    indexes (reference sources); Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1937 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 521)
    Scope and Content note
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows- both American and foreign. She discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries. She continues to develop nursing education programs around the country. Beard travels to Scandinavia and discusses public health nursing programs. The entries outline nursing education curriculum and legislation affecting them. She also travels to England where she details the measures that the Florence Nightingale International Foundation have adopted and haven't. Included are "Conference on Public Health Nursing" documents.
    Sweden; Diaries; Canada; United States; England; Nursing; Finland; Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
  - 1938 (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Frame 659)
    Organized according to interview and visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Mary Beard, professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both foreign and domestic. She summarizes the interviews with the current fellows. Beard attends numerous conferences and travels to the southern United States to detail public health nursing. Her travels take her to England and there she outlines the Florence Nightingale Foundation's objectives for their public health nursing programs as well as detailing public health nursing teacher qualifications for London University. Included are "conference o Eugenic and Birth Control of the American Eugenics Society" schedule and itinerary "Visits made by Miss Mary Beard in London on Wednesday July 13th and Thursday July 14th."
    Diaries; United States; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Public health nursing; Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary
- Beck, Glenn H.
  - 1969 (Box 31)
- Bell, Philip W.
  - 1963-1964 (Box 31)
  - 1965 (Box 31)
  - 1966 (Box 31)
- Bertheau, Rudolf C.
  - 1925-1928 (Box 31)
- Bevier, George
  - 1935 (Box 32)
  - 1936 (Box 32)
  - 1940, 1945-1947 (Box 32)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 32)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 33)
- Black, Joseph E.
  - 1963 (Box 33)
  - 1964 January-June (Box 33)
  - West Africa and Unindexed Diary, CHECK 1964 July-December (Box 34)
  - 1965 January-June (Box 34)
  - 1965 July-December (Box 34)
  - 1966 January-June (Box 35)
  - 1966 July-December (Box 35)
  - 1967 January-June (Box 35)
  - 1967 July-December (Box 36)
  - 1968 January-July (Box 36)
  - 1968 August-December (Box 36)
  - 1969 January-June (Box 37)
  - 1969 July-December (Box 37)
  - 1970 January-June (Box 37)
  - 1970 July-December (Box 38)
  - 1971 January-June (Box 38)
  - 1971 July-December (Box 38)
  - 1972 (Box 39)
  - 1973 (Box 39)
  - 1974 (Box 39)
  - 1975 (Box 40)
  - 1976 (Box 40)
  - 1977 (Box 40)
  - 1978 (Box 41)
- Boyce, Alfred Mullikin
  - 1968 (Box 41)
  - 1969 (Box 41)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 42)
- Brackett, Elizabeth W.
  - 1942-1943 (Box 42)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 42)
  - 1947 (Box 43)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 43)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 43)
  - 1952-1954 (Box 44)
- Bradfield, Richard